There's a company quietly holding the world's
software hostage, and no one is talking about it.
Broadcom, the eighth largest company
on earth, paid $69 billion for VMware.
You’ve probably never heard of it, but globally,
banks, grocery stores, telecom networks,
government agencies, all rely on it.
But after Broadcom bought it,
despite promising no price increases,
customers saw costs jump as much as 1000%.
They’re now fighting lawsuits from
the likes of AT&T, T-Mobile, Tesco,
while also fighting regulators, with one
fining Broadcom a quarter million euros a day.
Broadcom is even sending cease and
desists to their own customers.
The regulators who were supposed
to stop this — the FTC, the UK,
the European Commission — every
single one of them let it through.
Broadcom is holding the world’s software hostage,
and you and I may end up paying the price…
To find out how this happened, we need
to go back before the acquisition.
Because you might be thinking “How on
earth did regulators let this one through?”
A crucial question, that we’ll get to soon.
But first, what the heck is VMware,
and why does it matter?
VMware just means “Virtual Machine-ware”.
You might have heard that term, “virtual machine”.
It basically means a fake computer running
inside a real one.
This is how people
run Windows, even while on a Mac.
Sounds niche, but there’s a good
chance you interact with VMware every
single day, just without knowing it.
It was created in 1998, with the purpose of
running virtual machines on Intel’s x86 hardware,
and it solved a problem, which changed everything.
Before it, you could realistically only run one
“application” per physical server, because
if you ran multiple… and one crashes,
they all crash. It just wasn’t reliable.
So you had lots of small individual workloads
and servers, which only ran at about 10% capacity.
Because they’re separate, if use on one spikes,
it can’t draw from another which isn’t used.
Virtual machines solved this,
and this changed the world.
You can have one big server running
lots and lots of fake computers.
And if one crashes, it doesn’t
take the others down with it.
VMware meant more efficiency,
but also meant fewer servers, less cooling,
energy consumption usually drops by 80%.
This is quite simplified, and VMware
offers a lot of different software
products… but this affects, basically everything.
Online banking, grocery stores, telecom services,
major government infrastructure like tunnels
and bridges, VMware is huge, and everywhere.
VMware had become a near monopoly. It held
about 70% of the virtualization market.
But all this brings us back to Broadcom,
the 8th largest company on earth,
worth about 1.7 trillion dollars. Larger
than Meta, Tesla, and Saudi Aramco.
And the villain of our story: President Hock Tan.
Tan has a bit of a history here.
In 2018 he tried to buy Qualcomm, before he was
blocked by the Trump Administration, thankfully.
But soon enough, his eyes wandered to VMware,
and Tan saw a huge area of untapped revenue.
Unfortunately, it would make everyone else's
lives much worse, and Broadcom way more money.
But to the shock of many, the US, UK, and most
importantly, the EU all approved the acquisition.
In November 2023, Broadcom acquired VMware
for $61 billion, or at $69 billion including
VMware’s debt.
What? How?
How on earth did the Broadcom
takeover get approved?
And what did Tan have planned, that would end
with lawsuits, mass migration away from VMware,
and Broadcom sending cease and
desists… to existing customers?
Great question, because… I’m
still a bit confused myself.
Speaking of software, how many times have
you tried to learn a new coding language,
or coding in general, only to quit?
Ironically, in the age of vibe coding,
knowing code is more important than ever,
and gives you a big advantage in any career.
People across every industry are now
building their own apps and products.
And it’s never been easier to learn, with Coddy.
Coddy offers gamified and bite-sized coding
lessons, which quickly gets you writing
and learning code, through daily lessons.
Coddy tailors plans to you. Before you touch any
code, it’ll ask why you want to learn a language,
and what level you’re at.
Then, you learn by doing.
I was amazed how easy and fun the lessons are.
Coddy lessons give you an explanation, a quiz,
and practical exercise. So
it’s not just reading theory,
but it’s also not just looking at a page of code.
Learn a language by completing a journey. Improve
your skills with daily challenges. Or target your
weak spots with Coddy’s personalized practices,
which are tailored to your past
mistakes and your goals. Pretty cool!
Coddy is here to help those who are
meaning to learn to code, but can’t
quite find the time to dive deep into learning
it all. It’s built for people with no time,
and… honestly feels too good to be true.
Coddy might be the one that finally sticks,
and helps you level up your career.
Learn code today in a way that sticks,
by clicking the link in the description.
Thank you to Coddy for sponsoring this video.
The FTC, the Justice Department, the UK CMA, and
the European Commission, all made a fatal mistake…
They were all concerned with the risks
to the hardware market… not software.
The EU focused on fibre channel adapters,
the UK focused on server hardware components,
and the US raised a similar hardware issue, but
ultimately chose not to block the acquisition.
The risks here weren’t high enough to block
the deal… but none of them thought about what
would harm customers the most:
VMware’s licence structure.
In a blog in 2022 about VMware, Hock Tan wrote:
[Hock Tan, Broadcom President]: “The Broadcom
business case for this transaction is premised
on focusing the business model, increasing R&D,
and executing in getting customers to use the
full portfolio of innovative product offerings,
not on increasing prices.”
Sounds good right? But,
this is actually way worse. And notice
the “not on increasing prices“ part.
He also said “I’ve continued to
see questions in press reports
about whether we intend to raise prices on
VMware products. The answer is simple: No.”
Because this seems to contradict what followed.
After the acquisition, customer
costs went up across the board.
Managed service providers serving
doctors’ offices and small retailers saw a 10x
increase in cost, from around $50-70K per year,
to a minimum of $650K+.
A lot of businesses
saw price jumps of 300 to 400%.
European cloud providers saw cost hikes from
800% to 1,500%! Eight to fifteen times higher!
Tesco, the giant UK grocery chain, said some
VMware costs jumped around 175 percent, while
other VMware costs jumped 350%! Which it
described as “manifestly unfair and excessive.”
They even had an existing contract from 2021,
which Broadcom basically ignored.
But one of the biggest was AT&T
“After a 10 plus year strategic relationship with
Broadcom … I am sad to report that we appear to be
at an impasse on our VMware deal, This proposed
annual increase of +1,050 percent in one year is
extreme and certainly not how we expect strategic
partners to engage in doing business with AT&T.”
What followed, was outrage, lawsuits,
complaints to regulators, and much more.
But… Hock Tan promised he
wouldn’t increase prices…
Well, Broadcom didn’t technically.
They did something much worse.
Broadcom made two colossal changes:
They stopped selling perpetual VMware licences.
Previously customers bought
VMware once, and owned it forever.
And those customers still generated money,
because they paid for ongoing support from VMware.
Updates, security patches, support, etc.
But Broadcom, after the acquisition,
stopped providing paid security patches
and support… to existing perpetual
owners. Not that they wouldn’t update the
software, you couldn’t pay for it, at all.
For important infrastructure like VMware,
you can’t just not update it either.
Security needs to be continuously updated and
maintained, especially in cases like banks or
the government, where gaps in security
could have catastrophic consequences.
After the acquisition, Broadcom notified AT&T
that support for its roughly 75,000 virtual
machines running across 8,600 servers would end.
So how did existing customers… still use VMware?
That was the final part of the trap.
Broadcom was pushing perpetual
customers… to a new subscription.
But not just any subscription.
Broadcom reduced the VMware product catalogue
from over 70 product families, to just 4,
and gave customers just 30 days of notice.
This meant hundreds of standard products
people used, like individual SKUs,
great for small businesses, were gone.
You had to upgrade to the entire bundle,
either the VMware Cloud Foundation,
or the VMware vSphere Foundation. “All new
support must be via VCF or VVF subscription.”
That’s why all those companies, including
gigantic conglomerates, technically
had price hikes as high as 1000% or more.
This, is diabolical, but we’re not even done.
Broadcom sent cease and desists to their
own perpetual customers, against downloading
security patches.
Yeah.
But, you can’t just up and leave VMware.
It’s not software you can just change or
uninstall, for a lot of industries,
virtualization is very foundational.
It’s described as “bone-breaking engineering”.
Migrating is slow and expensive… and risky.
Exactly what Broadcom was counting on.
Perfect for someone who wants to upcharge
customers, as… they can’t really go
anywhere else. At least not quickly.
And what happened next, was all the ways it
backfired, some Broadcom didn’t anticipate.
But there might still be ways you and
I pay the price for this acquisition.
If you’ve watched this far, consider
subscribing! It helps the channel and
means you won’t miss future videos.
Hock Tan bragged that Broadcom got
more than 90% of VMware’s 10,000 largest
customers re-signed to new contracts.
But some of the actual largest, certainly
haven’t, and are fighting Broadcom at every turn.
First are the lawsuits.
AT&T sued Broadcom,
as it owned perpetual licences, and had a contract
that allowed it to extend support even further.
Broadcom, allegedly, went back on that contract.
This was especially important, because AT&T
had a 25 year contract for FirstNet. The
federal wireless first-responder network.
AT&T in the lawsuit said “Broadcom’s
attempt to bully AT&T into paying a
king’s ransom for subscriptions AT&T does
not want or need, or risk widespread network
outages that could cripple the operations
of millions of AT&T customers worldwide”.
And Broadcom’s response was… weird.
“If AT&T truly felt the support services
were essential to avoid irreparable harm to its
customers, it would have exercised and purchased
the ‘three-year-renewal’ option”
Odd.
The two eventually settled out of court,
but this is far from the only lawsuit.
T-Mobile also sued Broadcom, to
try to force Broadcom to keep
providing support for perpetual licences.
"In its complaint, T-Mobile said it has
tens of thousands of virtual machines using VMware
software across approximately 303,140 CPU cores.
It also said that it was migrating off VMware but
noted the time-consuming and technical challenges
involved in migrating over 1,000 applications."
Tesco is also suing Broadcom for over £100
million, and accused them of “abusive conduct”.
The grocery giant bought perpetual VMware licences
in 2021, with support through 2026, plus
the option to extend it another four years.
But, Tesco says Broadcom refused to continue
standalone support, which they already paid for,
and demanded they move to subscription
bundles, and pushed prices up ~175%.
But it gets even worse.
The Dutch Ministry of Infrastructure and
Water Management, which has used VMware for over
15 years, suddenly saw an 85 percent jump in cost,
to use the same software. From around
$2.4 million to nearly $4.6 million.
It asked Broadcom for a support extension
of two to three years while it migrated out,
which Broadcom refused, unless
it moved to a new platform.
This is a vital ministry which runs
the Netherlands’ tunnels, locks,
and bridges, essentially held hostage by Broadcom.
That was, until a Dutch Court found
Broadcom had breached its duty of care,
and ordered two years more support, at
reasonable cost, or be fined €250,000… per day.
Gotta say, that verdict feels pretty good to see.
This has also caused an EU trade body, CISPE,
to look much closer at Broadcom. CISPE sued,
not Broadcom, but the European Commission,
to void the original merger approval, arguing
regulators didn't properly scrutinise the deal.
Which, in fairness, is true. They didn’t.
Broadcom tried to fight back, bidding to
stop regulators requesting US
legal documents tied to VMware.
But the bid was denied, letting
the investigation continue.
There’s no doubt VMware is
making much more profit now.
VMware's operating margins went from 13–22%
pre-acquisition to 77% under Broadcom.
But long term, this may have
backfired spectacularly.
T-Mobile, Western Union, GEICO, Computershare,
Danfoss, are all moving away from VMware.
Regardless of the lawsuit outcome, Tesco has
also started migrating 40,000 servers away
from VMware. “The decision to migrate servers
while simultaneously suing the vendor reflects
how badly the relationship has broken down.”
“The VMware exodus is creating a market for
alternatives that did not exist two years ago.”
And it’s certainly helping competitors.
Competitor Nutanix’s CEO Rajiv Ramaswami described
the pace of Broadcom defections as “steady and
climbing”, and could continue for five years.
“I think there's no doubt that the customer
sentiment continues to be
negative about Broadcom,”
A survey of over 110 VMware customers in late
2024 found 98% are using, planning, or considering
alternatives to at least part of their VMware
estate, and 92% expect further price hikes.
CloudBolt estimated VMware’s virtualization market
share could drop from 70% to 40%, in just 5 years.
But, even so, for all the companies that just
decide to pay up, the cost might pass on to us.
Even if prices of everything don’t
immediately jump, companies often don’t
just “absorb” new costs without consequence.
Cloud providers absorb some, then slowly pass
on the rest to their own customers. Maybe not you
or me, but their own business customers, who buy
cloud hosting, who now have a higher IT cost.
Eventually, the end B2C product might
go up in price, or down in quality.
Or if governments have to pay Broadcom more
for virtualization, that's more tax dollars, more
of your money, which could go to other services.
As a report by ECCO, an industry group
representing European cloud companies,
stated “[VMware] price hikes have been absorbed
internally (at the expense of innovation) and
externally (at the expense of consumers).”
Broadcom took something people owned and
turned it into rent, but there’s another
company that set the trend for all this:
Adobe.
Turning owned software into a subscription, and
keeping customers trapped with excessive fees.
Now, they might just be getting what they deserve.
Watch this video next to learn more.